This daf is י"ז Yud-Zayin and we pick up at the two
dots on י"א ע"ב Yud-Alef Amud Beis where it's אמרי אוכלין ושותין
משחשיכה. amrei ochlin u’shotin mishechashecha. So we had a whole discussion, important
discussion yesterday about whether taking making a fast day for a personal
sort of religious pursuit is considered a good thing or a bad
thing and again that raises the interesting issues of the relationship that
I've been talking about about the יחיד yachid to the ציבור tzibur
because there you are separating yourself from the ציבור tzibur not as
the גמרא gemara discussed earlier by indulging in pleasure when the ציבור
tzibur is בצער betza’ar but for you know sort of accepting upon
yourself צער tza’ar when the ציבור tzibur is going about its normal
business and is that necessarily a good thing or a bad thing?
You know it's an important question. It's a very different type of
a תענית ta’anis than the תענית ta’anis that the גמרא gemara here
is dealing with or the you know מסכת maseches deals with which
is a תענית ta’anis specifically in the communal context and in the
context for rain. Anyway now we move on to the next section
of the משנה mishnah which is אוכלין ושותין משחשיכה ochlin u’shotin mishechashecha
about a third of the way down on י"א ע"ב Yud-Alef Amud
Beis that on these minor when the fast when the process of
fasting begins it starts first with the יחידים yechidim with the individuals
and then if it gets to ראש חודש כסלו Rosh Chodesh Kislev
and it still hasn't rained and it becomes a communal fast but
either the individuals or the communal is of the lighter nature because
you can eat at the previous eat and drink the previous night
and the other types of things are not forbidden like anointing and
bathing and sex and so on. Okay so that's true about the
first three of the individuals and then the first three of the
ציבור. tzibur. So the גמרא gemara says like this: אמר רב זירא
אמר רב הונא יחיד שקיבל עליו תענית אפילו אכל ושתה כל הלילה
למחר הוא מתפלל תפילת תענית. Amar Rav Zeira amar Rav Huna yachid
shekibel alav ta’anis afilu achal v’shata kol halailah l’machar hu mispallel tefillas
ta’anis. So the first statement is pretty much pretty straightforward based on
the משנה mishnah that if an individual accepts upon himself a תענית
ta’anis so either you're one of these יחידים yechidim and you're doing
it in the context of rain or you're just doing it for
your own purposes like the גמרא gemara discussed yesterday other you know
that there's a track that's not related to the rain but you're
accepting a private fast. So and you eat the night before because
as we've seen in our משנה mishnah certainly the fast of the
יחידים yechidim that begin is one that they eat the night before.
So למחר הוא מתפלל תפילת תענית l’machar hu mispallel tefillas ta’anis you're
still considered to be observing a תענית ta’anis and you say the
תפילת תענית tefillas ta’anis the next morning you know you say in
the שמונה עשרה. shemoneh esrei. So you and because it's still a
תענית ta’anis even though it's only starting in the day and it
doesn't include the night before. Yes so תוספות Tosafos observed I don't
even understand the חידוש chiddush I mean the משנה mishnah says that
that's considered the first three תעניתות ta’anios for the יחיד yachid and
the first three for the ציבור. tzibur. If it's considered the basic
statutory תענית ta’anis of course you מתפלל תפילת תענית. mispallel tefillas ta’anis.
So probably there's not much of a חידוש chiddush in that but
now we get on to the next point. And then it says
לן בתעניתו lan b’ta’aniso and in a way it's maybe said as
a contrast to say so if you sleep in your תענית ta’anis
meaning now it's מוצאי motzai your fast day and you didn't eat
let's consider like if we'll use one of our examples of a
historical fast it's the night after שבעה עשר בתמוז. Shivah Asar B'Tammuz.
So you ate the whole night leading into שבעה עשר בתמוז Shivah
Asar B'Tammuz and comes the day of שבעה עשר בתמוז Shivah Asar
B'Tammuz you're considered to be בתענית b’ta’anis and you say עננו. Aneinu.
Then comes the night of שבעה עשר בתמוז Shivah Asar B'Tammuz and
you do not and you don't have dinner that night and you
wake up the next morning so you still haven't eaten and now
you haven't eaten for like a full twenty-four hours right? לן בתעניתו
lan b’ta’aniso אינו מתפלל של תענית eino mispallel shel ta’anis comes שחרית
Shacharis of the eighteenth of תמוז Tammuz you don't say עננו Aneinu
you don't say because even though you're still fasting and here you've
been fasting for the prior twenty-four hours so you know it's like
it's a contrast. In the one case you ate ten minutes ago
you ate before עמוד השחר amud hashachar and comes שחרית Shacharis and
you say עננו. Aneinu. Here you haven't eaten for the last twenty-four
hours but you don't say עננו. Aneinu. You know why? Because you
have not accepted it as a תענית. ta’anis. It's true you haven't
eaten but because you have not accepted it as a תענית ta’anis
from the day before as we're going to see it doesn't have
the status of a תענית. ta’anis. So that's the reason he says
both the first statement as well is to create the contrast. Yes
Charlie. In our סידור siddur individuals don't say the עננו Aneinu during
שחרית. Shacharis. Okay I'll talk about when we say עננו Aneinu in
a minute okay? But anyway but that's his point okay? So one
case you ate ממש mamash an hour before and you're בתענית b’ta’anis
because you accepted it from the day before and then the other
day you fasted for twenty-four hours and you're not saying—yes? So רש"י
Rashi seems to make the point that that night מוצאי התענית motzai
hata’anis so you don't eat כל אותו הלילה לשם תענית kol oso
halailah leshem ta’anis in other words still has the כוונה kavanah to
be— Right, so that could be as well. You could be doing
it not just that you forgot to eat, but you could even
intentionally be fasting, but it's not officially a תענית. ta'anis. You just
you have not accepted, we don't know, but we'll assume that that's
the reason that you haven't accepted it starting the day before. But
let's see how the גמרא Gemara unpacks it. אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, let's see how the גמרא Gemara unpacks it. מאי קסבר
רב הונא? Mai Kasavar Rav Huna? What does רב הונא Rav Huna
hold? סבירא ליה Savra Lei אין מתענין לשעות, ein mit'anin lasha'os, או
דילמא o dilma מתענין לשעות, mit'anin lasha'os, ומתענה לשעות אינו מתפלל תפילת
עננו. u'mit'aneh lasha'os eino mitpalel tefillat Aneinu. So he says I'm going
to consider this continued fasting, the night following and the beginning of
the next morning, as a תענית שעות, ta'anis sha'os, for hours. Now
why exactly it's considered for hours? Every time you're in the morning
of a fast, you've only fasted a few hours, you haven't finished
yet. But again, presumably since you haven't accepted it from the day
before, and you know, it's also not clear, let's maybe even, maybe
it's not even your intention to finish the fast. Maybe it's only
your intention to go through the morning and then you're going to
have breakfast after שחרית. Shachris. So either because you didn't accept the
whole day as a fast, again, what the problem is not spelled
out here, or because you're not intentionally planning on fasting the whole
day, it's called a תענית שעות. ta'anis sha'os. It's only for hours.
It's not the whole unit of the day. So that's how he
identifies what's different about this case. And therefore I want to understand
what he holds. Does he hold that אין מתענין לשעות, ein mit'anin
lasha'os, that it's not considered a fasting at all, that even if
you were, you know, if you wanted to, let's say, eat right
now, you know, you could eat. There's no sense of being in
a fast if you're only planning, if you either haven't accepted it
the day before or you're only planning on doing it for part
of the day. It's not a full day fast. It has no
status at all and you can go ahead and eat if you
want to. There's no sense of violating any fast. או דילמא, O
dilma, מתענין לשעות, mit'anin lasha'os, no, there is some status of a
part-day fast and you would be considered to have fasted half the
day, but ומתענה לשעות u'mit'aneh lasha'os אינו מתפלל תפילת עננו. eino mitpalel
tefillat Aneinu. It's not enough to say עננו. Aneinu. עננו Aneinu is
for a full day fast, but there still is some status. So
the נפקא מינה nafka mina of these two is like number one,
am I allowed to just go ahead and start eating when I
want to? Is there a sense that I'm in the middle of
a part-day fast that that has some binding quality? Okay, maybe there's
some other נפקא מינה nafka mina if I accepted upon myself to
fast a certain number of days, can this maybe count towards the
fast? Okay, but that's the question. Is there some weight to this
as a part-day fast? But certainly not enough to say עננו. Aneinu.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so
אביי Abaye says back, לעולם קסבר רב הונא, le'olam kasavar Rav Huna,
רב הונא Rav Huna really holds מתענין לשעות, mit'anin lasha'os, ומתענה לשעות
מתפלל תפילת עננו. u'mit'aneh lasha'os mitpalel tefillat Aneinu. Actually, he holds that
it has a full weight. You can have a half-day fast and
if you fast for a half-day, you would say עננו. Aneinu. So
let's say you say, I'm going to fast until noon, I'm not
going to have any breakfast, I'm going to fast until noon, so
you're bound by that fast and during שחרית Shachris you'd say עננו.
Aneinu. So why is this any different? ושאני הכא דאיכא שבתא דמעליא
ולא קיבלה עליה מעיקרא. v'shani hacha d'ika shavata d'me'alya v'lo kibla alei
mei'ikara. Okay, so because, and here again that's why the גמרא Gemara
was ambiguous what the problem was, here it spells it out. The
problem isn't that you're planning on eating after שחרית, Shachris, or you're
planning on eating for lunch. The problem here was the weakness of
it was that you were not מקבל mekabel the fast from the
previous night. And therefore it does not have the weight. So this
is going to be two factors of a תענית ta'anis that the
גמרא Gemara is going to be moving back and forth about. Number
one is
it needs to be מקבל mekabel it the previous night to give
it the weight that's binding, that I just happen not to be
eating, but it has the status of a fast. And again, this
is
all by יחיד. yachid. By the
ציבור tzibur it's גוזרין, gozrin, you know, it's just
decreed that this
is
the תענית ציבור, ta'anis tzibur, it's not about my individual acceptance.
And the
other is the fact of
if it's part-day or a full day.
You know,
it's like the guy says, I'm fasting
between snacks, right? So how long do you have to be fasting
to give it that significance of a תענית? ta'anis? So those are
the two factors: the duration and the קבלה.
kabala. So the גמרא Gemara here says the problem is not
that you're planning on eating after שחרית Shachris or you're planning on
eating after lunch.
The problem here is
that it lacked the קבלה.
kabala. But presumably if you were מקבל mekabel a half-day fast, that
would be binding on you and you would say עננו. Aneinu. So
that's where the
גמרא Gemara is right now about the nature of this and why
it wasn't a תענית. ta'anis. I should say by the way just
to
answer
the issue of עננו, Aneinu, right, תוספות Tosafos raises the question about
when do we say עננו Aneinu when we do our fast, and
he quotes the בה"ג Bahag who says, if you take a look
at the end of תוספות למה בתעניתו, Tosafos lama b'ta'aniso, he says
like this. So he says in like about ten lines after the
תוספות Tosafos למה בתעניתו. Lama BeTa'aniso. One minute. So he says in
like about ten lines after the תוספות Tosafos למה בתעניתו Lama BeTa'aniso
starts, the line that starts with the word אכל, Achal, he says
ומפרש בהלכות גדולות, umefareish b'Hilchos Gedolos, right? הלכות גדולות, Hilchos Gedolos, thank
you, דאינו אומר עננו בתפילת שחרית, de'eino omer Aneinu bitfillat Shacharit, שמא
נמצא שקרן בתפילתו, shema nimtza shakran bitfillato, דשמא לא ישלים התענית, de'shema
lo yashlim hata'anis, right? That's our practice, that the individual doesn't say
עננו Aneinu because you might not complete the fast. ולי נראה, v'li
neereh, דלא נקרא שקרן, d'lo nikra shakran, כיון שהיה בדעתו להתענות, keivan
shehaya b'da'aso l'hisanos, אפילו אירעו אונס אחר כך, afilu ira'o ones achar
kach, ולא מצי להשלים נפשיה, v'lo matzi l'hasleim nafshai, because I don't
understand, even if something happened when it was שחרית, Shacharit, you were
planning on fasting the whole day, so why shouldn't you be able
to say עננו? Aneinu? And then if you skip to the bottom,
תוספות Tosafos says like this, וכתב... v'chosev... one minute, okay, ונוהגים, v'nohagim,
it's five lines from the bottom, last word on the line, ונוהגים
ששליח ציבור אומרו בשחרית, v'nohagim she'shliach tzibbur omero b'shacharis, כדי להודיע לעולם
ולהזכיר התענית. k'dei l'hodia l'olam u'l'hazkir hata'anis. So what? The שליח ציבור
Shliach Tzibbur says it in שחרית Shacharis to make it clear to
everybody that there is a fast day go on today. אבל יחיד
אינו אומר עד המנחה, aval yachid eino omer ad ha'mincha, but the
individual only says it at the מנחה Mincha following the practice of
the בה"ג, Bahag, except we have the שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibbur saying
it at the beginning. Right, I understand, but that's the practice. Anyway,
it's interesting he quotes the טור אורח חיים Tur Orach Chaim which
obviously is a later insertion into תוספות. Tosafos. Okay, so anyway, all
right, but that's actually how we get to our saying of עננו,
Aneinu, the גמרא Gemara it's not clear, the גמרא Gemara presumably
you were saying it at שחרית, Shacharit, yes. Okay, just to note
the Sephardic practice is that all
the יחידים yechidim say עננו Aneinu at שחרית. Shacharit. Okay, good to
know. Okay, also קבלה Kabbalah from the night before, does that must
be a verbal קבלה? Kabbalah? Okay, so we'll talk about that. That's
coming up later in the דף, daf, issue of קבלה, Kabbalah, yes.
And it's interesting, this sort of assumes that you're going to start
that the שליח
ציבור Shliach Tzibbur is going to remind everybody not to eat. I
mean today's day and age everybody's had something to drink before, you
know, like water or whatever. Not me, I'm very מחמיר machmir on
that. But you're right, right? Because... yeah, the assumption that you haven't
eaten or drunken before breakfast so you're going to... so right, exactly,
yeah, before שחרית, Shacharit, yeah. But is it that you have to
לקבל kabbal your fast for whatever period it is from
the period before? Meaning like if you're extending your fast in the
night time, you still don't say it in מעריב Maariv even though
you... Correct, you presumably even though the fast begins at the day,
you have to accept it from before, not just at the night,
even though you're still eating at the night but from the previous
day. But again, a lot of this stuff, some of this will
get spelled out as we continue, a lot of it is not
fully spelled out and תוספות Tosafos tries to figure it out, you
know, the ראשונים Rishonim try to figure it out, but a lot
of it remains pretty vague even at the end. Yes. Question
to Rabbi Larea, Sephardic practice at מעריב Maariv for ערבית Arvit say
עננו Aneinu on a fast that only begins in the day? I
can't imagine that you do that. On a fast that begins during
the day in the morning, do you say עננו Aneinu the night
before? No. No. And how about תשעה באב? Tisha B'Av? Yes. Okay,
all right. So now we say like this. Okay, so now we've
identified that the problem here is not that it's not a
full day
fast, but it hasn't had a קבלה. Kabbalah. מר עוקבא Mar Ukva
איקלע ikla לגינזק. l'Ginzak. Now מר עוקבא Mar Ukva came to this
place גינזק. Ginzak. בעו מיניה, Ba'u minei, they asked from him, מתענים
לשעות או אין מתענים לשעות, misanim l'sha'os o ein misanim l'sha'os, can
you do a part-day fast or not? לא הוה בידיה, Lo hava
b'yadei, he didn't know the answer. Wait, wait, קנקנים של נכרים, kankanin
shel nachrim, אסורים או מותרים? asurim o mutarim? Jugs of non-Jews that
they stored סתם יינם Stam Yeinam in it, wine of non-Jews in
it, but it was cold and so but they were porous because
they're pottery, what's the story, can you use them or not? לא
הוה בידיה, Lo hava b'yadei, he didn't have the answer. במאי שימש
משה כל שבעת ימי המילואים? B'mei shimish Moshe kol shiv'as yemei hamilu'im?
When משה Moshe was serving as the כהן Kohen during the ימי
המילואים, yemei hamilu'im, right, and he was inducting אהרן Aaron and the
sons, what clothing did he wear? He didn't have בגדי כהונה. bigdei
kehunah. לא הוה בידיה, Lo hava b'yadei, I have no idea how
these three are connected, I'm sure you can make a brilliant דרשה
drasha to connect these three. Anyway, אזל ושאאל בבי מדרשא. azal u'sha'al
b'bei midrasha. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, הלכתא hilchasa
מתענים לשעות ומתפלל תפילת תענית, misanim l'sha'os u'mispaleil tfillat ta'anis, you can
have a part-day fast and you can even say עננו. Aneinu. והלכתא
V'hilchasa like we said before, קנקנים של נכרים לאחר שנים עשר חודש
מותרים, kankanin shel nachrim l'achar shneim asar chodesh mutarim, that the jugs
of the non-Jews after twelve months you can use because whatever wine
got absorbed, you know, in the pottery is considered to now be,
you know, to not give any more taste, you know, to be
dissolved. Which actually, you know, leads to these interesting questions about China
after twelve months, etc. The difference here I should just say is
that this is all cold, this is not with heat, so that's
why it's important to note that this discussion is with things that
absorbed in cold. Okay. במאי שימש משה כל שבעת ימי המילואים? B'mei
shimish Moshe kol shiv'as yemei hamilu'im? בחלוק לבן. Be-chaluk lavan. He wore
a simple white white cloth. רב כהנא Rav Kahana מתני masni בחלוק
לבן שאין לו אמרא. be-chaluk lavan she'ein lo imra. He added that
there was no cuff to it, there was no stitching because then
this is based on a principle that you know, והייתם נקיים מה'
ומישראל, v'hisem nkiyim m'Hashem u'miYisrael, you don't want to think that you're
smuggling some stuff out in your hems. Okay. No sew nor hems,
right. אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav Chisda. Alright, so anyway that was
interesting but that basically just reinforced the idea that there is this
thing called תפילת תענית שעות Tefilat Taanit Shaot and they could even
and you would even say עננו. Anenu. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav
Chisda, let's get a little further. הא דאמרת מתענין לשעות והוא שלא
טעם כלום עד הערב. Ha d'amart mitanin l'shaot vehu shelo ta'am klum
ad ha'erev. So now it's so funny because there were two possible
issues of what made it a תענית שעות. Taanit Shaot. One is
it didn't have a formal קבלה. Kabbalah. So we said, oh, you
need to have a formal קבלה Kabbalah the night before or it
doesn't count as a תענית שעות. Taanit Shaot. Now we're saying the
other thing that made it תענית שעות Taanit Shaot was that you
only did it for part of the day. But now we're saying,
oh, if you want a תענית שעות Taanit Shaot to count, you
have to not eat until nightfall, the following night. So you accepted
it the previous night and you're not eating until the following night.
So what makes it exactly a תענית שעות? Taanit Shaot? So that's
what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye said: הא תעניתא
מעלייתא היא. Ha tanita ma'alyata hi. So that's a full תענית. Taanit.
It says, no, לא צריכא דאימלכא
אימלוכי.
Lo tzericha
d'imlecha imluchi.
You changed your mind. Which means what does it mean you changed
your mind? So one explanation is that, you know, you didn't eat
breakfast, it was a busy day, you weren't thinking exactly about fasting
and came along the middle of the day and you said, oh,
you know I've already fasted half of the day, I might as
well
finish
the rest of the day and not eat. Okay, and that's so
yes you didn't eat the whole day, but it wasn't
but
the first part
of it wasn't בתענית. be-taanit. The problem with that is that we
just said a little bit we said a minute ago that you
need to have a קבלה מעיקרא. Kabbalah me-ikara. So how do you
have like a קבלה מעיקרא Kabbalah me-ikara and then not, you know,
go and not go to the end of the day? So it's
and then still, you know, say דאימלכא אימלוכי. d'imlecha imluchi. So it's
very it's very unclear. רש"י Rashi says לא צריכא דאימלכא אימלוכי Lo
tzericha d'imlecha imluchi the ten lines down
in
the narrow
lines: לא היה בדעתו כלל להתענות אלא אנסו טירדא ולא אכל עד
חצי היום ובחמש
דחצי
היום ממלך
ואמר הואיל והתעניתי עד
חצי היום אסיים כל היום.
Lo haya bedato klal le-hitanot ela ansu tirda velo achal ad chatzi
hayom u-v'chamish d'chatzi hayom mimlach v'amar ho'il ve-hitaniti
ad chatzi hayom asayem kol hayom.
Okay, that's all sort of exactly as I described. It's all very
lovely, but it doesn't exactly explain,
you know, the
issue of what happened to
the idea of the קבלה מעיקרא. Kabbalah me-ikara. So תוספות Tosafot in
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah has another explanation of
this. I'm trying to remember it a little bit more complicated about
how you could get the two parts where you had the קבלה
מעיקרא Kabbalah me-ikara and you still did not it would not be
a it would not be a full תענית. Taanit. Did you change
your mind so you're going to eat but maybe you never did,
you'll still say עננו? Anenu? Yeah, but then it would never count
as a תענית שעות Taanit Shaot unless you finish it, right. Yes,
but then but it will never count but the idea that there's
such a thing as a תענית שעות Taanit Shaot now only works
if it was an accident, right? Because then under any normal circumstances
if you wanted it to work you'd have to basically do it,
you know, you'd have to do it as a full תענית. Taanit.
I'm not remembering how תוספות Tosafot explains it, you know, explains it,
but it's very hard to see these two גמרות Gemorot working together.
The easier explanation is is that these two are disagreeing, that the
previous גמרא Gemara assumes that yes you can do a half-day fast
but it needs a קבלה מעיקרא, Kabbalah me-ikara, and that's their idea
of a תענית שעות. Taanit Shaot. And this גמרא Gemara assumes that
you need a full day fast but it can count as a
תענית שעות Taanit Shaot in terms of your intention, that your intention
to to consider it a fast only began in the middle of
the day, did not come from the from did not come from
the night before. Is that clear? Meaning there are two possible components
that are missing. One is you didn't finish it, and one is
you didn't have a קבלה מעיקרא. Kabbalah me-ikara. The גמרא Gemara before
said you needed a קבלה מעיקרא. Kabbalah me-ikara. This גמרא Gemara says
you need to finish it. You combine them, it's hard to see
how it cannot be a full תענית. Taanit. So the easiest thing
to understand easiest way to understand this is that these two סוגיות
sugyot have different ideas of what a תענית שעות Taanit Shaot are.
The previous one assumes a תענית שעות Taanit Shaot is something that
literally you only you stop eating at midday, you you were מתענה
mitaneh till lunch and then you started eating, and this assumes a
תענית שעות Taanit Shaot is you fasted the whole day but the
whole day was not done as a תענית. Taanit. It was only
labeled a תענית Taanit in the middle of the day, it was
not labeled a
תענית Taanit from
the
beginning of the day. Okay, מעיקרא. me-ikara. But those two issues are
presumably that's the debate here, which one can be missing for it
to be considered תענית שעות. Taanit Shaot. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. ואמר רב חסדא: Ve-amar Rav Chisda: כל תענית שלא שקעה
עליו חמה לא שמיה תענית. Kol taanit she-lo shake-ah alav chama lo
she-mei taanit. Any תענית Taanit that the sun did not set does
not count as a תענית. Taanit. That you have to, which is
basically a way of reinforcing the idea before that you cannot have
a תענית Taanit that ends prior to the end of the day,
even a תענית שעות. Taanit Shaot. But it has to go till
the end of the day, till sunset. Now by the way I
should say
the language of שקעה עליו חמה shake-ah alav chama raises an interesting
question which is, so why do we wait till צאת Tzet for
the fast days? Right? And actually according to some ראשונים Rishonim you
don't have to. According to some ראשונים Rishonim other than something like
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and obviously יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know,
you can actually start eating כמשקיע. ke-mishki-ah. But nevertheless, you know, תוספות
Tosafot
and and the פסק psak has developed that either to read that
either to read שקיעת החמה Shkias HaChamah as תוספות'ס Tosafos's idea of
two שקיעות, Shkiahs, like a second שקיעה Shkiah which is basically closer
to צאת, Tzais, you know, to either read it that way or
to somehow say that, you know, but somehow say it doesn't it's
not meant literally, it says שקיעת החמה Shkias HaChamah but it really
means nightfall, but it is interesting, on the one hand this is
being framed as a חומרא, Chumra, it doesn't count as a תענית
Taanis if you do it if you end before nightfall, you have
to go till the end
of the night like we said even if it's a תענית שעות
Taanis Sha'os it has to go till שקיעה, Shkiah, it's being framed
as a חומרא, Chumra, but implicit in this is a קולא Kula
that you don't have to go beyond שקיעה, Shkiah, and we actually
don't פסקן Pasken that קולא, Kula, yes? I was at the
שערי חסד Shaarei Chesed synagogue once and they ended fast immediately after
they דאוון Davened מעריב. Maariv. Well, was it immediately after שקיעה? Shkiah?
Twenty minutes after שקיעה. Shkiah. So that's different, that's an early standard
of צאת, Tzais, you know? Okay, earliest moment. I personally, I personally
if you just want to know my own idiosyncrasies, I פסקן Pasken
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam for like שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom
Tov and תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you
know, which is seventy-two minutes, but when it comes to like the
minor fast days I פסקן Pasken like the הגר״א, Gra, which is
like literally it's thirteen minutes but I wait till like twenty-five minutes,
so anyway, so I sort of, so all right, I guess it
all evens out at the end, all right anyway so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, okay so now we have this idea, again
as opposed to before where it literally could have been a half
day presumably, here it's a full day but without קבלה Kabbalah and
that counts as a תענית Taanis or you know the labeling it
as a תענית Taanis only started in the middle, but here the
point is at the
end, emphasized, but whatever happens it has to go till שקיעה. Shkiah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, מיתיבי Meisivi I'll ask
you on this: אנשי משמר מתענים ולא משלימים. Anshei Mishmar misanim v'lo
mashlimim. So the people of the משמר, Mishmar, the כהנים Kohanim and
the לויים Levi'im that it was their cycle you know to the
כהנים Kohanim to work in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash that day and there were also corresponding
groups of לויים Levi'im and so on, they would fast the day
that they would be you know they'd be working in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but they would not go the whole day. So
the גמרא Gemara says, התם לצעורי נפשיה בעלמא הוא, Hasam l'tza'arei nafshei
b'alma hu, so you see there's a
sense
of תענית Taanis without
going till the end of
the day. Does לא משלימים Lo Mashlimim mean you give up? Or...
לא משלימים, Lo Mashlimim, שלם, Shalem, you do not complete
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם לצעורי נפשיה בעלמא הוא, Hasam
l'tza'arei nafshei b'alma hu, that doesn't that wasn't an official fast, they
were like not eating as a way of depriving themselves, and we'll
see when we get to the גמרא Gemara why that was, what
the idea of that was, but it was a way of expressing
some suffering, but it was not exactly a formal תענית. Taanis. Okay,
תא שמע, Ta Shma, come and hear, דאמר רבי אלעזר בר רבי
צדוק, D'amar Rabbi Elazar berabi Tzadok, אני מבני בניו של סנואה Ani
mibnei banav shel Sanav or סנאה Sana בן בנימין. ben Binyamin. So
we're going to find later a major focus of this
מסכת Masechet is these חגים Chaggim in מגילת תענית,
Megillas Taanis, these holidays that they would
that you would not be able to fast, and in particular ones
associated with days in which they would be when they returned from
the exile in the time of עזרא Ezra people donated families donated
wood to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for the מזבח,
Mizbeach, and those days that they made as a particular day of
the family to donate wood were established in the future as holidays
for that family, and that family would always in the future and
every future year, even if there was plenty of wood in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for the מזבח, Mizbeach, that family would make
a special holiday and give a gift of wood on that day,
and we'll discuss that when we get to it. And part of
the relevance is is that if that's your holiday then you don't
fast on that day. So here one and one of the holidays
of סנואה Sanav בן בנימין ben Binyamin was or
the holiday of סנואה Sanav בן בנימין ben Binyamin was the
tenth of אב, Av, okay right after תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. So
let's take a look. I am from that family ופעם אחת חל
תשעה באב להיות בשבת V'pa'am achas chal Tisha B'Av lihyos b'Shabbos and
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av was on שבת Shabbos ודחינוהו לאחר שבת v'dachinuho
l'achar Shabbos so then we observe תשעה באב Tisha B'Av on Sunday
the tenth, but that was my holiday והתענינו בו ולא השלמנוהו v'hisaneinu
bo v'lo hishlamnuho and we fasted but we didn't complete it מפני
שיום טוב שלנו הוא, mipnei she'Yom Tov shelanu hu, it
was our יום טוב Yom Tov so even if that'll even override
תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. So we didn't like not observe תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av at all but we didn't complete תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av.
So do you see there that how could he not observe תשעה
באב Tisha B'Av presumably even by not even though he didn't complete
it it still counted as a תענית, Taanis, the גמרא Gemara assumes,
otherwise like why observe it at all or otherwise how could he
have overridden it? And this after the חורבן?
Churban? Yes, it remains a holiday even after the חורבן. Churban. Okay,
תוספות Tosafos says it was either בטלה מגילת תענית לא בטלה מגילת
תענית Batlah Megillas Taanis Lo Batlah Megillas Taanis but yes for him
it remained a holiday after the חורבן. Churban. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, התם נמי לצעורי נפשיה בעלמא הוא, Hasam nami l'tza'arei nafshei
b'alma hu, so a very interesting answer. You know what? Because it
was his יום טוב Yom Tov it could have totally overridden תשעה
באב, Tisha B'Av, he could have technically eaten the whole day, it
was not like he got credit for fasting on תשעה באב. Tisha
B'Av. If you're not going to go to the end of the
day you don't get credit for fasting. But the reason he didn't
eat and
in a way it sort of evokes some of the גמרא Gemara
we had before about you know about being מרעיב עצמו Mariv atzmo
and
the ציבור Tzibur is
שרוי בצער, sharui b'tza'ar, you know, it'd be... participated in the affliction,
it has a status of afflicting himself, but it's not a תענית.
taanis. He didn't have to do it as a תענית taanis and
therefore he didn't complete it. But he didn't want to just set
himself apart from the ציבור tzibbur either. Yes.
Well, he was able to be דוחה doche תשעה באב, Tisha B'av,
but when תשעה באב Tisha B'av was pushed off to the tenth
of Av...
Ah, that's a very good point too. Right. It might not necessarily
have had the power to be דוחה תשעה באב בזמנו. doche Tisha
B'av Bizmano. It was דוחה נדחה, doche Nidche, right. It was a
good point. Yes.
This language would also go back to the point of תענית Taanis
as being a matter of prayer and not תשובה. Teshuva. Does this
suggest that that תענית taanis is not about suffering? In other words,
this was his personal צער, tza'ar, but but תענית taanis is something
different.
Well, I'm not sure I would go that far. It's just saying
that the suffering without the frame of תענית taanis is just suffering.
But like the גמרא Gemara before when it spoke about the idea
of is it good to be מתענה mit'aneh or not to be
מתענה, mit'aneh, יושב בתענית, yoshev betaanis, the גמרא Gemara if you remember
the top of י"א ע"ב Yud-Aleph Amud-Bes said, מצי לצעורי נפשיה דלא
מצי לצעורי נפשיה. matsi litsa'arei nafshei delo matsi litsa'arei nafshei.
Talking about whether it's fit to be מתענה mit'aneh or not מתענה.
mit'aneh. So I would disagree with that. I would not say מתענה
mit'aneh is not about suffering, it means but when you take away
the framing of תענית, taanis, all you're left with is just self-inflicted
suffering. Okay? But there's sometimes that there's a purpose to that because
you don't want to be indulging when everybody else is sitting in
a תענית... taanis... sitting in a תענית. taanis. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Abba Moshe. Right. So exactly like sitting on
a rock instead of sitting on a pillow. Exactly. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. תא שמע, Ta Shema, come and hear. דאמר
רבי יוחנן, D'amar Rabbi Yochanan, אהא בתענית עד שאבוא לביתי. ehei betaanis
ad she'avo leveisi. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say, now it's very
funny, דאמר רבי יוחנן d'amar Rabbi Yochanan sounds like רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is saying a halakhic statement, which is normally how you introduce
it, but here it's really saying that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself
would say from time to time, "I'll be in a תענית taanis
until I get to my house." Like again, like fasting between snacks.
Okay, so here was, so he was traveling on the road, so
you see it was a תענית taanis without the day completing. He
said אהא בתענית. ehei betaanis. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הכא
משום ביעותי נפשיה מבי נשיאה הוא דעבד. hacha mishum bi'utei nafshei mibei
nesi'a hu d'avid. There he did it because he was afraid that
the בי נשיאה's bei nesi'a house would sort of would demand that
he, you know, that he'd come and come for a meal and
come invite him over, so he says, "No, no, no, I'm in
a תענית, taanis, I can't I can't join you for the meal."
Okay.
Okay. It's like the opposite of the line somebody told me the
other day, says two questions that the answer is always yes to.
One is "Have you davened מנחה?" Mincha? and the other is "Are
you מילכיג?" milchig?
So anyway, so here he wanted the answer always to be no,
like "No, I'm sorry, I've already eaten, I can't join you." Anyway,
alright. So that wasn't a real תענית. taanis. אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel.
Okay. So now, so that again underscored the need to complete, right,
as as we said that probably was ignoring the weight of the
need for קבלה מבעוד יום kabbalah mibe'od yom or else what are
you left with in terms of תענית שעות? taanis sha'os? But here
שמואל Shmuel now is going to revisit the importance of קבלה מבעוד
יום. kabbalah mibe'od yom. So let's take a look. אמר שמואל, Amar
Shmuel, כל תענית שלא קיבל עליו מבעוד יום לא שמיה תענית. kol
taanis shelo kibel alav mibe'od yom lo shemei taanis. Right? So you
have רב חסדא Rav Chisda saying אם לא שקע עליו חמה לא
שמיה תענית im lo shakal alav chama lo shemei taanis and שמואל
Shmuel saying if you do not מקבל מבעוד יום mekabbel mibe'od yom
לא שמיה תענית. lo shemei taanis. So again,
once you combine these two, it's pretty impossible to figure out how
you're ever going to get a תענית שעות. taanis sha'os. Okay, so
presumably as we said, תענית שעות taanis sha'os is one or the
other. But now we have, now we've underscored the need of going
until שקיעה shkia and now שמואל Shmuel saying the need for קבלה
מבעוד יום. kabbalah mibe'od yom. ואי יתיב מאי? v'iyasiv mai?
Now let's say you went ahead and you fasted the whole day,
but you didn't have a קבלה kabbalah the day before. What does
that, what's the significance of that? So אמר רבה בר שילא, amar
Rabbah bar Shila, דמי למפוחא דמליא זיקא. dami lemapucha demalya zika.
You are like a bellows filled with air. Basically, you filled your
body with air, but it's worthless. You don't get any credit. You
didn't do anything meaningful. It doesn't count as a תענית. taanis. You
don't say עננו. Aneinu. It's nothing. It's a very, very graphic image.
So אימת מקבלה? eimas makbileh?
When do you accept it upon yourself? So רבא Rava אמר במנחה,
amar b'Mincha, at מנחה, Mincha, which means by context מנחה Mincha time,
not during מנחה Mincha itself. Because ושמואל u'Shmuel אמר, amar, the same
שמואל Shmuel who said that you need קיבל עליו מבעוד יום, kibel
alav mibe'od yom, says בתפילת המנחה, bitfillas haMincha,
during the prayer of מנחה, Mincha, you actually do it at, you
know, in the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Okay, now that's important because
because again, going to this issue about the relationship of תענית taanis
to תפילה, tefillah, right, if it's just some type of a קבלה
kabbalah like some type of a נדר, neder, which is an idea
we'll see before, why exactly does that belong in שמונה עשרה? Shmoneh
Esrei? Like the idea of doing it in the afternoon because it's
before the day begins, right, that makes sense, right, why it needs
מנחה Mincha time. You might even want to say it's פלג המנחה,
plag haMincha, you know, really close to the... the end of the
day. But why does it need מנחה? Mincha? So again, maybe it's
easier to remember if you have a fixed place to do it
in, but you know, but people if you want to accept the
תענית, Taanit, you normally is the thought that flies through somebody's head.
Why don't they just say it? Why do they have to incorporate
it into the דאוונען? Davening? So presumably this again shows the relationship
of תענית Taanit to תפילה, Tefillah, but we're not done. Yes, Michael,
what's your question?
Is this only for a personal fast?
Yes, personal fast.
The fact that none of us are מקבל mekabel a public fast
at מנחה Mincha before? What? None of us are מקבל mekabel a
public fast at מנחה Mincha before.
Right, right, right. This is all personal fast. Otherwise because it doesn't
say but that's the whole context of all of this, right? And
the משנה Mishnah remember still is also about the יחידים, yechidim, although
the second part of the משנה Mishnah is about the ציבור. tzibur.
But yes, this is all about a personal fast. Now where you
accept it also is interesting. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, כל
תענית שלא שקעה, Kol Taanit Shelo Shaka,
תוספות Tosafot says the first wide line he says, כל תענית צריך
לקבלו מבעוד יום בתפילת המנחה בשומע תפילה ואם הוא שבת באלהי נצור.
Kol taanit tzarich lekablo mibaod yom bitefillat hamincha beshomea tefillah veim hu
shabbat beelohai netzor. Okay,
because שבת Shabbat you don't have שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah, okay, but
is the fact that you're saying it in שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah,
what the heck does your personal קבלה kabbalah to fast tomorrow have
to do with שומע תפילה? Shomea Tefillah? It's not a prayer you're
making to God, right? You're making a personal קבלה. kabbalah. So but
the point is if the purpose of a תענית Taanit is for
God to be שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah, if תענית Taanit is connected
to תפילה Tefillah in a way of, you know, having our prayers
heard, I think there's a power. Now again, that we see much
more by the תענית ציבור, Taanit Tzibur, or the תענית Taanit of
the יחידים yechidim that's leading into the תענית ציבור Taanit Tzibur of
this מסכת, masechet, that it's about an intensifier of prayer, right? A
personal תענית, Taanit, you know, maybe it's because we're going to find
out later, as you know a major reason they made a תענית
Taanit was תענית חלום, Taanit Chalom, I have a bad dream, I
feel that maybe somehow by doing a תענית Taanit thatll, you know,
negate the portents of the bad dream, or maybe I'm doing it
as just my own personal religious practice, it's not so clear why
personal תענית Taanit is connected to תפילה Tefillah the way that the
תעניות Taaniyot of this מסכת masechet are. But nevertheless it is, you
know, significant that we have this connection in שמואל Shmuel and in
the תוספות Tosafot saying that it even occurs in שומע תפילה. Shomea
Tefillah. I should also mention by the way the other interesting point
about this and about thinking about like a תענית שעות Taanit Shaot
as opposed to a day of תענית Taanit is the fact that
you need מבעוד יום, mibeod yom, right? On one hand even though
the fasting on these minor fasts or on a personal fast begins
in the morning, you need the קבלה kabbalah the previous day, right?
You need the קבלה kabbalah to be not the night before but
the מנחה Mincha before, right? Why not the night before it's still
before I'm starting to fast? Because we're viewing it not just as
a personal practice, I'm accepting on myself to do a practice of
not eating. In a way the personal practice is just צערי נפשיה,
tzaarei nafshiah, I'm just okay I'm not eating, that's what I'm doing,
I'm just afflicting myself. A תענית Taanit gives somehow status to not
the act that I'm doing but the thing I did was a
fast and maybe even the day was a יום תענית. yom Taanit.
So to give status to that day it has to occur even
before nightfall, even though the fasting itself won't begin until the morning.
רב משה Rav Moshe has a fascinating שאלה shaila going to historical
fasts and communal ones as opposed to personal ones, but do the
three weeks begin, you know, the night of שבעה עשר בתמוז? Shiva
Asar B'Tammuz? Can you go to like a wedding the night of
שבעה עשר בתמוז Shiva Asar B'Tammuz or do something else? It feels
a little inappropriate but it raises, he gets into this interesting question,
right, about the fasting, the practice begins in the morning, but the
status of the day might begin when the day begins, right, the
night before. So the idea that even though the fasting begins in
the morning, the קבלה kabbalah has to occur already before, you know,
nightfall. Yes.
Is this סוגיא, sugya, is there a parallel to the סוגיות sugyot
in ברכות Berachot around page 15, like personal prayers at the end
of the עמידה? Amidah?
Yes, although that's again that's right, תוספות Tosafot is discussing in שומע
תפילה Shomea Tefillah again that's not in the גמרא, Gemara, but yes.
But yes, and but again that raises the question of its relationship
to תפילה. Tefillah. Let's take a look. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, says רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, כוותיה דשמואל מסתברא, Kevatei deShmuel mistabera,
like שמואל Shmuel makes sense, דכתיב dechtiv במגילת תענית, beMegillat Taanit, and
notice the language דכתיב, dechtiv, right, it's written, the same type of
language you'd use if it's something was in a biblical verse, but
that's because מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit actually was written and was not
part of the, you know, oral culture. It was written and again
this is a short scroll from the time of already going back
to בית שני Bayit Sheni that had in it a list of
the days that you could not fast, a list of the minor
holidays, okay? And it's written in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit the
following: להן כל איניש דייתי עלוהי מקדמת דנא, Lehen kol inish deyaasi
alohi mikadmat dena, any person that brought that, you know, that is
brought upon himself from prior to this, meaning that accepted upon himself
to fast prior to these days, these holidays, יאסר, yeasar, shall be
forbidden to fast, meaning these are days that you are not allowed
to fast. I'm sorry,
יאסר, yeasar, shall be
forbidden. prior then you remain forbidden by your by your קבלה. kabbalah.
Now exactly what that means in terms of what do you mean
you remain forbidden? Does it mean you remain forbidden if it doesn't
contradict one of these holidays? Or that if your קבלה kabbalah preceded
these holidays, then you go ahead and fast even when you encounter
these holidays? Okay, we'll bracket that for a minute, but we're just
going to focus on the language of יאסר, yeaser, which shall be
bound or be forbidden. מאי לאו יאסר עצמו בצלו mai lav yeaser
atzmo betzalu shall forbid himself in prayer, meaning that the קבלה kabbalah
happens in prayer? So גמרא gemara says לא, lo, no, יאסר עצמו,
yeaser atzmo, no, just means forbid yourself by a קבלה kabbalah but
without prayer. Now of course what where did you get one vehicle
over the other? Who cares if it's written with two יודים yudin
or written with an אלף? alef? How does one imply in prayer
and the other imply not in prayer? So the point here is
it's very hard to argue why one or the other, but this
here is the best edition of מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit came out
recently from ורד נעם, Vered Noam, very nice thick heavy book also
written very heavy paper. Anyway, very heavy book, but just so you
have a sense of how small the actual מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit
is, and you know a lot of this is like manuscripts and
notes and so on. Here's the whole מגילה, megillah, okay? This tiny
little text up here, not all this stuff, okay? It says אתחיל
מגילת תענית, atchil Megillat Taanit, okay, which is how they describe it,
אלין יומיא דלא להתענא בהון, ilin yomaya dela lehitana behon, here are
the days not to fast, ומקצתהון דלא למספד בהון umiktzathon dela lemispad
behon and some of these days you can't even give a הספד.
hesped. And then it says מריש ירחא דניסן תמניא ביה merish yarcha
deNisan tamnya bei from Rosh Chodesh Nisan until the eighth, and then
it lists dates, ירבן לק, yerban lak, like, like so just listing
dates,
בארבעה בתמוז, bearbaa betamuz, בעשרין וארבעה ביה, beasrin vearbaa bei, like listing
dates, right, this date, this date, this date, gives like three words
about what happened on each day. Okay, it goes on, basically it's
and the whole thing is thirty-eight short lines. You see I mean
how long the lines are? The whole מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit is
thirty-eight lines, and then the very last line of מגילת תענית Megillat
Taanit says,
right, it goes through אדר Adar because it starts with
ניסן, Nisan, so בעשרין ותמניא ביה אתת בשורתא טבתא ליהודאי דלא יעדון
מן אורייתא ולא למספד. beasrin vetamnya bei atat besurta tavta lihudai dela
yadun min oraita vela lemispad. So that's the 28th of אדר, Adar,
and then the very last line of מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit says
להן אינש דאיתי עלוהי יאסר בצלו. lahen inish deiti alohi yeaser betzalu.
So notice the word it had that wasn't in our גמרא, gemara,
בצלו, betzalu, in prayer. Okay, therefore a person that brings this upon
himself is forbidden in prayer. Now that's a pretty ambiguous phrase what
that means, but the point is this text has the word בצלו
betzalu in the text itself. And a number of manuscripts of this
גמרא gemara had when the גמרא gemara actually quoted מגילת תענית, Megillat
Taanit, it had דכתיב במגילת תענית להן כל אינש דיאסר עלוהי מקמתנא
יאסר בצלו, dechativ biMegillat Taanit lahen kol inish dyeaser alohi mikamatna yeaser
betzalu, actually had the quote בצלו betzalu in prayer. Okay, and therefore
the debate in the גמרא gemara was not how do you interpret
the word יאסר, yeaser, but whether your גרסא girsa of מגילת תענית
Megillat Taanit have the word בצלו betzalu or not. Okay, and that
was the question. In מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit when it refers to
accepting a fast, does it refer does it have the word בצלו
betzalu in prayer in there or does it not have that word
in there in מגילת תענית? Megillat Taanit? So either it's a question
of interpreting what the word יאסר yeaser means, but more simply it
was a question of what your גרסא girsa of מגילת תענית Megillat
Taanit was, whether you had the word in prayer or not. So
that's the debate. Who edits? This is ורד נעם. Vered Noam. Okay,
now most of a lot of the after that short list of
days what you have is something that already the בבלי Bavli knows
of and quotes from, which is called the סכוליון, scholyon, the סכוליא,
scholia, סכוליא, scholia, it's pronounced סכוליא scholya or סכוליא. scholia.
Whatever. סכוליון scholyon is what I understood.
Right, that's the singular, I
understand singular, right.
Okay, anyway, so so that is the one that really elaborates on
what happened in those days and often that was written later than
the original מגילה, megillah, and that was written more in the like,
you know, probably like אמורא, amora, אמוראי amoraic period, although some of
it actually shows later influence of incorporating things in the בבלי Bavli
and retrofitting them into it, but it did precede the אמוראים amoraim
and often when they quote מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit, they're quoting the
סכוליון scholyon and not just the short מגילה megillah which was just
the list of days. Okay, but anyway, the גמרא gemara says look,
it says in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit you forbid yourself in prayer.
It says nah, maybe take out the word prayer or maybe that's
not what it means. Okay, פליגי בה רבי חייא ורבי שמעון ברבי,
peligi ba Rabbi Chiyya veRabbi Shimon berebbi, they have a debate. חד
אמר יאסר וחד אמר יאסר. chad amar yeaser vechad amar yeaser. Again,
we're somehow assuming that יאסר yeaser means with two יודים yudin the
way our גרסא girsa the גמרא gemara has it or very different
גרסאות girsot of the גמרא, gemara, but with our גרסא girsa the
גמרא gemara it means in prayer as opposed to יאסר yeaser which
just means a simple make it forbidden on yourself. מאן דאמר יאסר
כדאמרן. man damar yeaser kedamran. למאן דאמר יאסר מאי היא? leman damar
yeaser mai hi? דתניא במגילת תענית, detanya biMegillat Taanit, so now here
we said we talked notice here moved from דכתיב dechativ to דתניא,
detanya, okay, cause now it's quoting the סכוליון. scholyon. So the סכוליון
scholyon is not דכתיב, dechativ, is not the actual, you know, short
written scroll itself. itself it is a later elaboration and that's seen
more as a type of a you know of an oral text
and not as much of a written text.
So דתניא במגילת תענית, detanya b'Megillat Taanit, we taught in מגילת תענית:
Megillat Taanit: כל אינש דייסי עלוהי מקדמת דנא יאסר, kol inish d'yasi
alohi mikadmat dena ye'aser, כיצד. keitzad. So now this is the Scholion
that elaborates on what that line means of that you forbid yourself.
יחיד שקיבל עליו שני וחמישי של כל השנה כולה, yachid shekibel alav
sheni v'chamishi shel kol hashana kula, if an individual decided—and this is
fascinating, it shows you how far back this idea goes of fasting,
right, not in the context of תענית ציבור, ta'anit tzibur, not in
the context of rain, just personal fasts, you know, and the גמרא
Gemara before was reflecting is it a good thing or a bad
thing, it's clear that this was a widespread practice or at least
not a rare practice. So therefore, it says in the Scholion of
מגילת תענית: Megillat Taanit: somebody who accepted upon himself to fast every
Monday and Thursday of the entire year, וארעו בהם ימים טובים הכתובים
במגילת תענית, v'iru bahem yamim tovim haktuvim b'Megillat Taanit, and these ימים
טובים yamim tovim come about, אם נדרו קודם לגזירתנו, im nidro kodem
ligzeiratenu, if his vow preceded our גזירה, gezeira, our decreeing these days
as ימים טובים, yamim tovim, יבטל נדרו את גזירתנו. yevatel nidro et
gezeiratenu. So his נדר neder overrides our vow and he fasts on
these days. ואם גזירתנו קודמת לנדרו, v'im gezeiratenu kodemet lenidro, however, if
our vow, our decreeing these days, preceded his vow, so then תבטל
גזירתנו את נדרו, tevatel gezeiratenu et nidro, our גזירה gezeira wins out.
So that's why it says if he was—again, going back to the
line that we had before: כל אינש דייסי עלוהי מקדמת דנא, kol
inish d'yasi alohi mikadmat dena, if you had accepted upon yourself prior
to these dates of the מגילה, Megilla, then you remain forbidden. If
you were there first, you went out; if we were there first,
we went out. Now the question is, what does it mean were
there first? So, you know, does it mean that you started fasting
before you encountered one of our dates? That would almost always happen.
The only exception to that would be you actually began your fasting
on the date itself. But then it means anytime the fast began
earlier, you always override. So then when is there ever going to
be a time like, you know, what's the whole point of this
מגילה? Megilla? You're always going—the other one's always going to win out.
So basically, רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both read this as—take a
look at תוספות—oh Tosafot no, that's a different point. But anyway, both
read this as saying that it means that you made your vow
before we
declared this day a יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it means that—so
then it's very rare, meaning that, you know, like as soon as
this thing is written down, the only purpose
of writing that was for like the year in which that thing
was being written down. You know, but any year after that it's
all irrelevant because it's already written and these days are already decreed.
But it really means that if you had your vow prior to
the day—you're basically the phrase we have is you're grandfathered in. If
you had your vow prior to us announcing these new days, you
keep your vow. But otherwise, once these days are on the calendar,
then you have to give up, then your vow does, you know,
gets pushed off. Now what happens to your vow if it encountered
one of these days? So then there's a debate of whether you
have to make it up on another day. And now we're getting
to this idea of being משלים. mashlim. If you look at
תוספות: Tosafot: ואם גזירתנו קודם לנדרו ידחה נדרו מפני גזירתנו, v'im gezeiratenu
kodem lenidro yidache nidro mipnei gezeiratenu, אומר רש"י ידחה נדרו מכל וכל
ולא ישלים אותו תענית, omer Rashi yidache nidro mikol v'chol v'lo yashlim
oto ta'anit, ואני מסופק בדבר ויש להחמיר. v'ani mesupak badavar v'yesh l'hachmir.
Okay, so that if it actually does encounter, you have an idea
of making up. And this is going to be an interesting thing
of תענית—where ta'anit else do we have an idea of making up?
תפילה. Tefilla. Right, so this becomes very interesting of an idea of
that it's—that it says somebody you can make up. But part of
it also is again because we think of it as a thing,
not just as a practice. Like it's not just I am vowing
on Thursday that on Thursday I'm not going to eat. Okay, then
if I ate on Thursday because it was a יום טוב Yom
Tov or whatever I had to, whatever, then I violated my vow
or something, but it doesn't mean that Friday replaces Thursday, right? I
made a vow about Thursday. But if it's an idea that there's
this thing called a תענית ta'anit and I'm going to—I'm going to
do five תעניתים, ta'anitim, right? I will pay up five—you know, I
will sort of do five fasts and there are units of things
that I'm doing, so maybe I can do them on a different
day even though it wasn't the day that I was intending of
doing it on. So again there's a certain type of an
objectifying—I don't mean that in the way we use it now, but
of a reifying, of a creating this fast not just as a
practice but as a thing, right? And that's again going back to
the idea of a נדר neder from the day before, making it
up, counting how many you're doing, and you know, paying them off
on a different day and so on. Yes.
And we do have that idea for the public
fast already.
That there's an idea of being
נדחה. nidcha. Right, the day of observance. But here it's not
like—true—but here there's more of like of a flexibility if—well, that is
true, תוספות Tosafot gets to the question of do you do it
the immediate next day, do you have to pay it up eventually
and sometime, but you're right, I still think that there's a difference
here because there it's like the question of which day is תשעה
באב Tisha B'Av observed is different than the question of I made
a נדר neder to do this and now I'm just going to
and I made it to do it on a particular I'm going
to do it on a yeah.
Should I assume that this נדר Neder was a mistake, right? Otherwise
it would be like a נדר לשוא? Neder Lashav? Is there such
a, it's just such a?
What do you mean it was a mistake? Do you mean because
it conflicts with a יום טוב? Yom Tov? Well that's exactly the
point I'm making it. I'm making if this was just a נדר
Neder of practice, so then fine, so then maybe it turns out
that it was a נדר שוא Neder Shav or maybe it turns
out you know you transgressed your נדר. Neder. Right, but the idea
that you can still make it up shows that we don't just
focus on a נדר Neder to do practice X on day Y,
that there's like I will
give X number of fasts. You don't give it or you don't
pay it up on this day, you know, I pay it up
on a different day. But it also raises important questions about the
whole use of נדר, Neder, because נדר Neder usually is not about
doing something, but נדר Neder is about creating a status on something.
But that also might be related, because what you are doing is
you are creating the status of a day as a יום תענית,
Yom Ta'anit, you know, as opposed to personal practice. So there's a
lot to be unpacked here about the about how the idea about
this phenomenon of personal תענית Ta'anit and the mechanism with which it
operates. Okay, yes, that makes sense. Right, and a נזיר Nazir makes
a נדר, Neder, is true, and that's about his personal status.
That's a good comparison. Exactly.
Right, yes,
he has to be משלים, Mashlim, that's true. That's a that's a
good point as well.
It kind
of
describes the whole thing.
But like assuming when a person makes a נדר, Neder, you know,
he he's every Monday and Thursday, but he also knows Pesach is
on Monday. Right, so the so that's somehow implicit in the נדר
Neder is that it's adjusted for, right. That's that is true, you
could basically say it means like that's, you know, that's already implicit
in the נדר Neder and to be adjusted accordingly when it interrupts
with certain dates, right. You didn't have Outlook coming on and saying
that your recurring event conflicts with something on your calendar.
All right, moving on. So, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught: אימתי
אוכל ושותה, Eimatai ochel v'shoteh, until when, now we're going back to
the idea that you this is again a minor fast, maybe we're
back to the mishna that it's the יחידים yechidim that are fasting
or maybe the ציבור, tzibur, but it's the ones that you can
eat the previous night. So till when can you eat if you've
been eating the previous night? So עד שיעלה עמוד השחר, ad sheya'aleh
amud hashachar, until the morning star which is halachically when the day
begins about 72 minutes before sunrise. דברי רבי, Divrei Rabbi, that's what
Rabbi says. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon omer:
עד קריאת הגבר, ad krias hagever, until the cock crows. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, I don't know whether that's when that is exactly, but
it's after. What?
It's earlier than the morning star? I think it's generally assumed to
be after. Yeah. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: לא שנו אלא שלא גמר
סעודתו.
lo shanu ela shelo
gamar seudaso. When is it that you can keep on eating? This
is very important, right, that, you know, it's going to be let's
say שבעה עשר בתמוז Shiva Asar B'Tammuz or whatever, you go to
sleep, can you set your alarm wake up at 4 a.m. before
עמוד השחר amud hashachar and have breakfast? A lot of people, yeah,
I sometimes do that, not so often. But anyway, so he says
that you can eat until the until עמוד השחר amud hashachar is
only if you didn't finish your meal from the night before. אבל
גמר סעודתו, aval gamar seudaso, once you've finished your meal and you
benched or whatever, אינו אוכל, eino ochel, then that implicitly shows that
you are already beginning your fast. איתיבי, Eiseivei, the Gemara says I'll
ask you on this: רבא גמר ועמד, Rava gamar v'amad, הרי זה
אוכל. harei zeh ochel.
איתיבי רבה, Eiseivei Rava, or איתיבי אביי, Eiseivei Abaye, excuse me, גמר
ועמד הרי זה אוכל. gamar v'amad harei zeh ochel. If you finish
and you get up from your meal, you can still continue to
eat, so it's not like you said. התם כשלא סילק, hasam k'shelo
silek, that's when you did not like remove the table, you know,
remove the food off the table. You might have benched and got
up but the food's still on the table. But once you clear
away the table then you're then you're locked in. Right, איכא דאמרי,
ika d'amri, right, איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some say אמר רבה: amar
Rava: לא שנו אלא כשלא ישן. lo shanu ela k'shelo yashan. אבל
ישן אינו אוכל. aval yashan eino ochel. Once you've gone to sleep,
as long as you haven't slept, you can always go back to
be eating. Once you've gone to sleep, it's showing that like, okay,
you're into the next
day already and now you're bound by it. So איתיבי אביי, Eiseivei
Abaye, Abaye asks him this: ישן ועמד הרי זה אוכל. yashan v'amad
harei zeh ochel. Even if you went to sleep, if you got
up you can continue to eat. התם במתנמנם, hasam b'misnamnem,
that's when you didn't really go to fast sleep, that's when you
were like dozing. היכי דמי מתנמנם? Heichi dami misnamnem? What is dozing?
So אמר רב אשי: amar Rav Ashi: נים ולא נים, nim v'lo
nim, it's like you're asleep but you're not asleep. תיר ולא תיר,
teir v'lo teir, you're awake but you're not really awake. דקרו ליה
ועני, d'kru leh v'anei, that somebody calls you and you answer. ולא
ידע אהדורי סברא, v'lo yada ahadorei svara, but you can't say anything
of reason, right? You can't say anything you can't give a reason
a coherent, you're not coherent. Thank you. וכי מדכרו ליה מדכר, v'chi
madkru leh madkar, if they remind you, you remember. So somebody calls
you to say
where'd you leave the car keys,
like oh, I don't know
whatever, did you leave them there, yeah, yeah, whatever. Anyway, so hopefully
then you're by then you're saying the right answer. Anyway, all right.
So anyway, but if you go fast asleep... Sleep not, but of
course the הלכה halacha *halacha* actually is that if you have in
mind that you're not being מקבל *mekabel* the תענית taanis *ta'anit* and
you're planning on waking up and you set your alarm, so if
you accidentally woke up before עמוד השחר *amud hashachar* and you were
planning not to, then you can't actually go ahead and eat. But
if you set your alarm or you were planning to or you
were thinking I might wake up and if I do wake up
I'll eat, then you are allowed. Again this is quite interesting, right,
because the fasting really only begins in the day. It's only a
day fast, but somehow at a certain stage once you are done
with the eating, you know, that really does somehow begin the תענית
taanit *ta'anit* even earlier. Where does that mechanism come in? Like where
does that come in? And again that shows the idea that to
some degree the whole day is a יום תענית taanis *yom ta'anit*.
Although you're only doing the actual practice of fasting come the morning,
the whole day is labeled a יום תענית *yom ta'anit*, so once
you are done with your eating, eating is allowed the evening of
the יום התענית *yom hata'anit*, but it still is a יום התענית
*yom hata'anit*. So therefore once you're done with your eating and you're
you know then you move into the normal practices of the day.
So again it shows something about the status of the day. It's
not something that just begins in the morning. The whole idea of
סעודה המפסקת *seudah mafseket* you know comes from the idea that this
is the last סעודה *seudah* you eat and that then it ends
the eating. Okay, so let's go a little bit further. אמר רב
חנא אמר רב יחיד yachid שקבל עליו תענית אסור בנעילת הסנדל *Amar
Rav Chana amar Rav Yachid shekibel alav ta'anit asur binedilat hasandal*. So
an individual that accepts a תענית *ta'anit*, although a תענית יחיד *ta'anit
yachid* is one that as we've been discussing started in the day
and the other types of עינויים *inuyim* are permissible. He says nevertheless
you should not put on shoes and presumably do the other עינויים
*inuyim* either. Why? חשינן שמא תענית ציבור taanit tzibur. קבל עליו *Chashinan
shema ta'anit tzibur kibel alav*. So maybe when he accepted a תענית
*ta'anit*, he wasn't clear that he was accepting only a תענית יחיד
*ta'anit yachid*, maybe he was accepting the תענית ציבור taanit tzibur *ta'anit
tzibur* and therefore it starts the night. Logically then it should start
the night before and it should have all these other components to
it. Now again that is a fascinating idea. How could you accept
a תענית ציבור taanit tzibur *ta'anit tzibur*? You're a יחיד *yachid*. What
do you mean?
Yes this whole thing.
Right, what do you mean? I mean תענית ציבור tzibur *ta'anit tzibur*
is something that a ציבור tzibur *tzibur* does. So again what it
shows you is that there's this thing, this object called a תענית
ציבור *ta'anit tzibur*. And the nature of a תענית ציבור *ta'anit tzibur*
like you know is a type of a fast that starts the
night before that has all these other עינויים *inuyim* etc. So you're
a יחיד *yachid* if you're saying in your דאוונען *davening* because we're
supposed to say it in דאוונען *davening*, הריני בתענית ציבור למחר *Hareini
beta'anit tzibur lemachar*, rather than saying that that's an absurd thing to
say, no, it's like saying you know I'll have one of the
blue ones instead of one of the yellow ones. I'll take the
תענית ציבור *ta'anit tzibur* rather than the תענית יחיד *ta'anis yachid*. It's
a type of a thing that you can do and that is
now that is you know with all these extra עינויים *inuyim*. So
again it's thingifying, it's reifying you know
this idea of I can add a fancy word and my turn
anyway. So but now Chavi is going to say what do you
mean the earlier משנה *mishna* says that a תענית ציבור
*ta'anit tzibur* exactly
right starts in the day and you're allowed to do all these
things. Yes that's the beginning, but the first three are lighter. Once
being once we get to like hitting our stride as we're going
to see in the next משנה *mishna*, the full-blown תענית ציבור *ta'anit
tzibur* is the night before you know no bathing, no shoes etc.
and that's seen as classic תענית ציבור *ta'anit tzibur*. So when שמואל
*Shmuel* says for example אין תענית ציבור בבבל אלא תשעה באב בלבד
ein taanit tzibur biBavel ela Tisha B'Av bilvad *ein ta'anit tzibur beBavel
ela tisha be'Av bilvad*, he means the תענית ציבור *ta'anit tzibur* is
the full-blown the night before the extra עינויים *inuyim*. So תענית ציבור
*ta'anit tzibur* is used as a descriptor for this idea of the
full-blown complete fast. Okay, so we're afraid that that's the one he
accepted upon himself. So the גמרא *Gemara* says היכי לעביד *heichi le'avid*,
what should you do to avoid this confusion? אמר רבה בר רב
שילא לימא הכי *Amar Raba bar Rav Shila leima hachi*, say the
following: למחר *lemachar* and here's the language אהא לפניך בתענית יחיד *ehei
lefanecha beta'anit yachid*, say explicitly. Okay it's interesting by the way the
word לפניך *lefanecha*. You're saying it in דאוונען *davening*, so you're talking
to God. Presumably either in שומע תפילה *Shomea Tefillah* because the גמרא
*Gemara* doesn't say where, תוספות *Tosafot* says שומע תפילה *Shomea Tefillah*. But
again it's interesting it's in דאוונען *davening* so you're addressing God לפניך
*lefanecha*. But again it also gets to I think this question of
תענית *ta'anit* and תפילה *tefillah* to be in תענית לפניך *ta'anit lefanecha*
like דע לפני מי אתה עומד *da lifnei mi atah omeid*, like
the idea of this sort of way that the observance of the
תענית *ta'anit* is like the standing in prayer, I think that there's
some echo there. אמרי ליה רבנן לרב ששת *Amrei lei rabanan leRav
Sheshet*, so the rabbis said to רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*, הכא חזינן
רבנן דמסיימי מסיינייהו ואתו לבי תעניתא *hakach chazeinan rabanan demesaymi mesaynayhu ve'atu
levei ta'anita*, we see the rabbinic students put on their shoes and
they come to an interesting phrase, the house of the תענית *ta'anis*,
presumably meaning the שול shul *shul* where we're observing a תענית *ta'anis*.
Okay, which is bizarre, apparently it was a תענית ציבור *ta'anit tzibur*
and therefore it should have been אסור *asur* for to put on
shoes. איקפיד *itpid* he got he got upset ואמר להו *ve'amar lehu*
he said to the rabbinic students דילמא מיכל נמי אכול *dilema meichol
nami achol* maybe you're also eating? So what is this you're putting
on shoes during a תענית *ta'anis*? So now we're going to see
what it's about. אביי ורבא Abaye veRava *Abaye veRava*... אביי ורבא that
was presumably a בי תענית bei taanis means it was a communal
תענית and they were still putting on shoes. אביי ורבא מאי לכון
סיימי הפנצא mai leichun saimei hapantza Abaye and Rava would come into
presumably again the שול or something when they were wearing a הפנצא
hapantza which is some type of a shoe not a full shoe
maybe didn't have a full sole or something but some type of
a slipper. מרמר מר זוטרא Maremar Mar Zutra מחלפי דימינא לשמאלא ודשמאלא
לימינא. machalfei d'ymina l'shmala u'd'shmala l'ymina. So they still wanted to wear
shoes but so funny that shoes are the big deal to me
eating the night before is the big deal but maybe this was
the most visible people don't see maybe they smell but they don't
see if you've bathed they don't see other things but they see
if you're wearing shoes so this was the publicly observable aspect of
are you treating this as a תענית ציבור. So they wanted to
wear shoes so they did a שינוי shinuy they put the right
on the left and the left on the right but we're going
to see that normally wouldn't be allowed the reason about all of
these is because they really פסקן pasken there's no תענית ציבור בבבל
biBavel like I mentioned before. רבנן דבי רב אשי Rabanan debei Rav
Ashi נפקי כי אורחייהו nafkei ki'orchayhu and the rabbis the rabbinic students
of Rav Ashi's house they went out like normal with their shoes
on their normal feet סברי savri they held כי הא דאמר שמואל
ki'ha d'amar Shmuel like Shmuel says אין תענית ציבור בבבל biBavel אלא
תשעה באב בלבד which again means not that there's never will be
a communal תענית it sounds like there was a communal תענית going
on but it never gets to the weight of what's labeled a
תענית ציבור which means starting the night before not wearing shoes not
bathing not having sex those things that weight is not in בבבל
biBavel בבבל never needs rain to that degree and therefore even a
communal fast never has those things and that's why these rabbis were
wearing shoes but it presumably they פסקן paskened that way but presumably
the ציבור wasn't aware of you know the practice of the ציבור
you know really was adopting not to wear shoes and there was
this whole issue about how they were being perceived as not participating
again it gets to this יחיד וציבור yachid v'tzibur here the יחיד
is being more lenient right you're acting in a way because you
know the הלכה it's all very nice but you seem to be
standing out as separate from the community in terms of its observance
of the fast.
Okay
so we will continue this tomorrow.
Okay today is mentioned on מגילת תענית.
Megillat Taanit. Oh really what what's the